Guide to the John Borsdamm Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John Borsdamm papers
1930-1972
SC0510
Borsdamm, John.
1.5 Linear feet
These papers pertain to Borsdamm's career as bookbinder and consist primarily of letters received, with some biographical materials, clippings, ephemera, and two photographs of Borsdamm. The bound volume, "Letters of appreciation to John Borsdamm on the occassion of his retirement from Stanford University Press, June 1, 1950," includes letters from J. E. Wallace Sterling, Herbert Hoover, Jessie Knight Jordan, Pedro deLemos (Pedro J. Lemos), William F. Durand, Carol Green Wilson, David S. Jacobson, Ray Lyman Wilbur, and Borsdamm's colleagues at the Press. Of note are letters from Julius A. Quelle and Jessie Dunten Whittern recounting the history of the Press. The papers also include the original design of a phoenix by Nathan Van Patten that was used on the binding Borsdamm did for THE LETTERS OF D. H. LAWRENCE.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Gift of Felicia Hassell Pearce, 1996.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
John Borsdamm, bookbinder, joined the Stanford University Press in 1915. He was born in Germany and served an apprendiceship as bookbinder in Leipzig before coming to the United States. His work was exhibited at the Golden Gate Exposition in 1939 and elsewhere. While at the Press, he designed the "Borsdamm Binding," an economical method of binding papers and magazines for library use. He retired in 1960.
Description of the Collection
These papers pertain to Borsdamm's career as bookbinder and consist primarily of letters received, with some biographical materials, clippings, ephemera, and two photographs of Borsdamm. The bound volume, "Letters of appreciation to John Borsdamm on the occassion of his retirement from Stanford University Press, June 1, 1950," includes letters from J. E. Wallace Sterling, Herbert Hoover, Jessie Knight Jordan, Pedro deLemos (Pedro J. Lemos), William F. Durand, Carol Green Wilson, David S. Jacobson, Ray Lyman Wilbur, and Borsdamm's colleagues at the Press. Of note are letters from Julius A. Quelle and Jessie Dunten Whittern recounting the history of the Press. The papers also include the original design of a phoenix by Nathan Van Patten that was used on the binding Borsdamm did for THE LETTERS OF D. H. LAWRENCE.
Access Terms
Borsdamm, John.; Durand, William Frederick, 1859-1958; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Jacobson, David S.; Jordan, Jessie Knight, 1867?-1952; Lemos, Pedro J. (Pedro Joseph), 1882-1945; Quelle, Julius A.; Stanford University. Press.; Van Patten, Nathan, 1887-1956.; Whittern, Jessie Dunten.; Wilson, Carol Green, 1892-; Bookbinding.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Biographical clippings and notices (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book Week Exhibition (S.U. Libraries), 1934 - program and clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Borsdamm, Mrs. Gertrude - letter received 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Galvin, John A. T. - letter to Borsdamm, 1964, and clippings on Galvin, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hoover, Herbert - letters to Borsdamm, 1938-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Leather samples, stamped (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous items - clippings and ephemera (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Non-Stanford correspondence, 1943-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs (2) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stanford correspondence, 1930-1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Suttenfield, George - letters received re commemorative book of letters for Borsdamm, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman - letters to Borsdamm, 1936-1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - [Nathan Van Patten], phoenix design for D. H. Lawrence binding (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bound volume: Letters of appreciation to John Borsdamm on the occasion of his retirement from Stanford University Press, June 1, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)